<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE feature_key_file [
   <!ELEMENT feature_key_file (comments, feature+)>
   <!ELEMENT comments (#PCDATA)>
   <!ELEMENT feature (name, description?, is_sequential, parallel_dimensions)>
   <!ELEMENT name (#PCDATA)>
   <!ELEMENT description (#PCDATA)>
   <!ELEMENT is_sequential (#PCDATA)>
   <!ELEMENT parallel_dimensions (#PCDATA)>
]>

<feature_key_file>

   <comments></comments>

   <feature>
      <name>Basic Pitch Histogram</name>
      <description>A feature vector consisting of bin magnitudes of the basic pitch histogram described in the jSymbolic manual. Each bin corresponds to one of the 128 MIDI pitches, ordered from lowest to highest, and with an interval of a semitone between each (enharmonic equivalents are assigned the same pitch number). Bin 60 corresponds to middle C. The magnitude of of each bin is proportional to the the number of times notes occurred at the bin's pitch in the piece, relative to all other pitches in the piece (the histogram is normalized).</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>128</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Pitch Class Histogram</name>
      <description>A feature vector consisting of bin magnitudes of the pitch class histogram described in the jSymbolic manual. Each bin corresponds to one of the 12 pitch classes, ordered in increasing pitch with an interval of a semitone between each (enharmonic equivalents are assigned the same pitch class number). The first bin corresponds to the most common pitch class in the piece under consideration (it does NOT correspond to a set pitch class). The magnitude of of each bin is proportional to the the number of times notes occurred at the bin's pitch class in the piece, relative to all other pitch classes in the piece (the histogram is normalized).</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>12</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Number of Pitches</name>
      <description>Number of unique pitches that occur at least once in the piece. Enharmonic equivalents are grouped together for the purpose of this calculation.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Number of Pitch Classes</name>
      <description>Number of pitch classes that occur at least once in the piece. Enharmonic equivalents are grouped together for the purpose of this calculation.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Range</name>
      <description>Difference in semitones between the highest and lowest pitches.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Strong Tonal Centres</name>
      <description>Number of isolated peaks in the fifths pitch histogram that each individually account for at least 9% of all notes in the piece.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Mean Pitch</name>
      <description>Mean MIDI pitch value, averaged across all pitched notes in the piece. Set to 0 if there are no pitched notes.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Mean Pitch Class</name>
      <description>Mean pitch class value, averaged across all pitched notes in the piece. A value of 0 corresponds to a mean pitch class of C, and pitches increase chromatically by semitone in integer units from there (e.g. a value of 2 would mean that D is the mean pitch class). Enharmonic equivalents are treated as a single pitch class.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Most Common Pitch</name>
      <description>MIDI pitch value of the most frequently occuring pitch.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Most Common Pitch Class</name>
      <description>The pitch class that occurs most frequently compared to other pitch classes. A value of 0 corresponds to C, and pitches increase chromatically by semitone in integer untis (e.g. a value of 2 would mean that D is the most common pitch class). Enharmonic equivalents are treated as a single pitch class.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Interval Between Most Prevalent Pitches</name>
      <description>Absolute value of the difference (in semitones) between the pitches of the two most frequently occurring pitches.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Pitch Variability</name>
      <description>Standard deviation of the MIDI pitches of all pitched notes in the piece. Provides a measure of how close the pitches as a whole are to the mean pitch.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Major or Minor</name>
      <description>Whether the piece is major or minor, as indicated by the first encountered major/minor metadata tag in the piece. Set to 0 if the metadata indicates that the piece is major, or set to 1 if the metadata indicates that it is minor. Defaults to 0 if the key signature is unknown.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Most Common Melodic Interval</name>
      <description>Number of semitones corresponding to the most frequently occurring melodic interval.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Amount of Arpeggiation</name>
      <description>Fraction of melodic intervals that are repeated notes, minor thirds, major thirds, perfect fifths, minor sevenths, major sevenths, octaves, minor tenths or major tenths. This is only a very approximate measure of the amount of arpeggiation in the music, of course.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Repeated Notes</name>
      <description>Fraction of melodic intervals that correspond to repeated notes.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Direction of Melodic Motion</name>
      <description>Fraction of melodic intervals that are rising in pitch. Set to zero if no rising or falling melodic intervals are found.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Melodic Pitch Variety</name>
      <description>Average number of notes that go by in a MIDI channel before a note's pitch is repeated (including the repeated note itself). This is calculated across each channel individually before being combined. Notes that occur simultaneously on the same MIDI tick are only counted as one note for the purpose of this calculation. Notes that do not recur after 16 notes in the same channel are not included in this calculation. Set to 0 if there are no qualifying repeated notes in the piece.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>1</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Chord Type Histogram</name>
      <description>A feature vector consisting of bin magnitudes of the chord type histogram described in the jSymbolic manual. This is a normalized histogram that has bins labeled with types of chords (in the following order and with the indicated identifying codes): partial chords consisting of just two pitch classes [0], minor triads [1], major triads [2], diminished triads [3], augmented triads [4], other triads [5], minor seventh chords [6], dominant seventh chords [7], major seventh chords [8], other chords consisting of four pitch classes [9], and complex chords with more than four pitch classes [10]. The bin magnitudes are calculated by going through MIDI ticks one by one and incrementing the counter for the bin that corresponds to the chord, if any, that is present during eah given tick; the result is that the chords in this histogram are weighted by the duration with which each chord is played. All inversions are treated as equivalent and octave doubling is ignored in the calculation of this histogram. Melodic behaviour is not considered, so arpeggios are not counted in this histogram.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>11</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

   <feature>
      <name>Pitched Instruments Present</name>
      <description>A feature vector indicating which pitched instruments are present. Has one entry for each of the 128 General MIDI Instrument patches (0 is Acoustic Piano, 40 is Violin, etc.). Each value is set to 1 if at least one note is played using the corresponding patch, or to 0 if that patch is never used.</description>
      <is_sequential>true</is_sequential>
      <parallel_dimensions>128</parallel_dimensions>
   </feature>

</feature_key_file>